<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copy of a letter sent by one of the camp, of the Prince of Conde (touching the feats of war as of late haue been doon) to a freend of his, the xxx. of December last past. Anno Domini. 1568</title>
            <author>One of the camp, of the Prince of Conde.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1569</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06381</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16853</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107743</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843439</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843439</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06381)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 476:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copy of a letter sent by one of the camp, of the Prince of Conde (touching the feats of war as of late haue been doon) to a freend of his, the xxx. of December last past. Anno Domini. 1568</title>
                  <author>One of the camp, of the Prince of Conde.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>At the long shop adioyning vnto S. Mildreds Churche in the Pultrie, by John Allde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. 1569. Ianuarij. 24. [1569]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Condé, Louis, --  prince de, 1530-1569.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8173:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8173:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figure>
                     <p>I A</p>
                     <figDesc>initials of the printer John Allde</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <p>I A</p>
                     <figDesc>initials of the printer John Allde</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE COPY OF</hi> a letter ſent by one of the camp, of the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> (tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the featꝭ of war as of late haue been doon) to a fréend of his, the xxx. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> laſt paſt.</p>
                  <p>Anno Domini. 1568.</p>
                  <p>Laus Deo.</p>
                  <q xml:lang="lat">¶ Omnia Vincit Veritas.</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8173:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8173:2"/>
            <head>OF A LETTER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter your depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (moſt honourable) out of Fraunce, we haue own nothing but ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning to and fro<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> taking &amp; lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſiege to Towns and Citties, and all what wée haue taken in hand: hath proſpered wel and gone forward, God haue the honour for it. And yet wée wil not ceaſſe, or leaue of: but go forward as place and time ſhall ſerue. And as we neuer douted of your good wil, and earneſt deſire to ſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of Gods &amp; our enemies: ſo now we ſée efféctually ſhewed your redy help and preſent comfort. And as wée haue had before in our e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trepriſes, or atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pts good ſuccedings: ſo now we truſte to doo the better, for your ayd which you haue ſent vs. Not becauſe we put any truſt, or confidence eyther in our ſelues, or in any outwarde force: but that they are meanes, wherby our God I truſt ſhall deliuer vs, and that ſhortly. God forbid that wée ſhould make fleſhe or blood our arme, or to put anye conridence in the
<pb facs="tcp:8173:3"/>
multitude of horſemen. Neuertheleſſe wée are many, and our number is thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thouſand footmen, of the which ther are fiue and twentie thouſand Harke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſiers, or Gunners, and the reſt wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned with Launces, and ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or eight thouſand horſemen: beſide the multy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming from <hi>Montaban.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for our victories whiche God hath giuen vs: wée haue taken by force of weapon theſe townes following.
<list>
                  <item>S. Iehan Dangeli.</item>
                  <item>Fontenay.</item>
                  <item>Angouleſme.</item>
                  <item>Chaueni. néer Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers.</item>
                  <item>Chammi.</item>
                  <item>Lodun.</item>
                  <item>Biſamni.</item>
                  <item>Ambeteni.</item>
                  <item>Toillebourg.</item>
                  <item>Niort.</item>
                  <item>Partenay.</item>
                  <item>Pont.</item>
                  <item>Penni.</item>
                  <item>Talmond.</item>
                  <item>Montagni.</item>
                  <item>Blay.</item>
                  <item>Bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>niu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>et.</item>
                  <item>Sainctes.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And other more as <hi>Coingnac, New caſtel</hi> Bréeflye all what lyes vpon the riuer of <hi>Garro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne</hi> vntil the riuer of <hi>Loyre</hi> on the ſide of <hi>Samne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the battails or ſkirmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhings whiche we haue had againſt our enemies, we haue béen together twiſe
<pb facs="tcp:8173:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or thriſe, in ſuche a place, and field, as they might haue choſen for their aduan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tage to fight, wheras they were ſo layd an: that neuer ſince they durſt méet vs any more, but alwayes auoyd and flée our companie, ſmelling vs a far of as a Fore dooth the pitched line.</p>
            <p>Touching the méeting and a ſkirmiſhe betwéen vs fiue wéeks ago: they loſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or eyght hundreth men, &amp; the ſpoile was about two hundreth M. crownes worthe, but they ſaued them ſelues by the means of a riuer, ſome within <hi>Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers,</hi> ſome other at <hi>Luſignam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> caught the hat of an Italian Capitaine named <hi>Peter Strocij.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lorde Admiral, the Coate of one <hi>Briſac.</hi> My Lord the Duke <hi>Montgomery</hi> the ſtirrops and ſpurres of <hi>Monſieur</hi> of Guiſe.</p>
            <p>One of my Lord Admirals lackeis hath for his part ſixe and thirtie péeces of ſiluer veſſels whiche did belonge to the lord of Guiſe. To be ſhort: ther was none of them al but that they were th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> better for it. After that my Lords the
<pb facs="tcp:8173:4"/>
Princes being of minde to prouoke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fight a battail: applyed them ſelues in their fight towards the Towne and Caſtle of <hi>Chagny,</hi> a fortreſſe where as they truſted them ſelues for to be moſt ſure, but theſe good ſoules had rather to ſaue them ſelues by flying then to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Townes &amp; Caſtels, or to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to a Combat: for they ſay it is dangerous, to be there as their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon terme was at that time throughe out all their camp, as ſince it hath béen very often practiſed by them, louing ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to flée and to forſake their Towns and cities: then to hazard their liues, or to put in ieobardie their bodies, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the whiche they hope to be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. So the ſaid Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> being néer <hi>Samny,</hi> for to haue beſieged it: our enemies approched with their Artiſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry within a quarter of a leagne of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dun,</hi> and required it to be rendred, wher of the Prince béeing aduertiſed: made haſte towards them in ſuche ſorte that they were conſtrained to break vp their ſiege and to go againe to their olde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed remedy, whiche is to get the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:8173:4"/>
away ouer the riuer. True it is that b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they came ſo far, there were ſlaine two hundred of their men, &amp; the night following, ſeuen Enſignes more were vndoon and deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Moreouer two dayes paſt the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of <hi>Monſieur du Noye,</hi> ouertook, and found at the ſubburbs of the afore ſayd town <hi>Chagny:</hi> about thrée or four ſcore Zwitſers.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Prouoſt and Archers of the Garde of my Lord the Kings brother, which was him ſelf within the Town. And beyond the water was an Alarme very hote.</p>
            <p>This day there came newes by two Gentlemen whiche arriued comming fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Bipont,</hi> whiche left the ſaid Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> within ſeuen &amp; twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie leagues of <hi>Paris,</hi> hauing with him ten or eleuen thouſand Kutters, or Horſemen, and foure thouſand frenche men, and ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téen or ſeuentéen thouſand footmen, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che take their journey ſtraight toward <hi>Paris,</hi> of the whiche armie <hi>Monſieur, de Iauliis</hi> leadeth the firſt warde. And the
<pb facs="tcp:8173:5"/>
ſaid Duke of <hi>Bipont</hi> hath béen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming toward the prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> euer ſince the tenth day of this Moneth, to ioyne him ſelf with him.</p>
            <p>Alſo newes came aſwel in our camp, as alſo to oure enemies, that <hi>Monſieur D'arnalle</hi> hath loſt foure thouſand men, being conſtrayned throughe the armie of the Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> (whiche came to ioine him ſelf to the Duke of <hi>Bipont</hi>) to retire ſudenlye with two thouſand men whiche were left him to go to <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens.</hi> It is ſaid for a trouth that the Lord <hi>Guiſe</hi> is gone in poſte to finde out the King. Alſo it is ſaid that the moſte patt of there camp goeth toward <hi>Paris,</hi> to ſet the againſt the ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Princes. I beleeue wée ſhall follow. <hi>Cito.</hi> Cito.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London at the long</hi> Shop adioyning vnto S. Mildreds Churche in the Pultrie, by Iohn Allde Anno Domini. 1569, Ianuarij. 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8173:5"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
